Finding Aid for G. Mennen Williams Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Governor's Papers
  - Executive Office, 1949-1960
    - Foreign Trips
      Foreign Trips includes itineraries, correspondence, and lists of contacts relating to foreign trips taken by Governor and Mrs. Williams together and separately from 1955-1960. The trips included Israel, 1955; South America, 1956; Liberia, 1958; Israel and Western Europe, 1959; South America, 1960; and Nancy Williams; 1959 trip for the World Health Organization on which she examined health problems and health facilities.
      - Israel, 1955
        - Notebooks and lists of contacts (Box 408)
      - South America, 1956
        - Correspondence (Box 408)
          (thank yous)
        - Background and correspondence of Brazil and Puerto Rico; Governor's speech in Puerto Rico (Box 408)
      - Liberia, 1958
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 408)
        - Lists of contacts, correspondence, programs (Box 408)
      - Israel and Western Europe, 1959
        (include correspondence, itineraries, thank-yous, etc.)
        - France (Box 408)
        - Germany, October 21, 1959 (Box 408)
          (includes Governor's memo of his conversation with Konrad Adenauer)
        - Greece (Box 408)
        - Israel (Box 408)
        - Italy (Box 408)
        - Jordan (Box 408)
        - Lebanon (Box 408)
        - Poland (Box 408)
        - Switzerland (Box 408)
      - Israel and Western Europe, 1959
        (include correspondence, itineraries, thank-yous, etc)
        - Lists of contacts made on trip (Box 409)
        - Letters received from Michigan and U. S. about trip, 2 folders (Box 409)
        - Outline of slides taken in Israel (Box 409)
        - Governor's letters home, 18 folders (Box 409)
        - Newsclippings of Governor's letters home (Box 409)
        - Small notebook of G. Mennen Williams (Box 409)
      - South America, 1960
        - Notebook and 1 folder of Governor's letters home (Box 409)
          (notebook includes Nancy's letters from WHO trip, 1959)
        - Governor's articles for the Detroit Free Press (Box 409)
        - Correspondence and office memos (Box 409)
        - Information on trip sent by Governor's Conference (Box 409)
        - Itinerary (Box 409)
        - Speeches given on trip (Box 409)
        - Thank-yous written by GMW (Box 409)
        - Clippings (Box 409)
        - Background information and speeches by South American dignitaries, 1 volume (Box 409)
      - Nancy Williams WHO trip, 1959
        - Nancy Williams biography (Box 410)
        - India (Box 410)
          (correspondence)
        - Japan (Box 410)
          (biographies, correspondence)
        - Rangoon, Burma, Afghanistan (Box 410)
          (biographies, itineraries)
        - Korea (Box 410)
          (lists of contacts, correspondence)
        - Singapore, Thailand (Box 410)
          (lists of contacts, itinerary, correspondence)
        - Philippine Islands (Box 410)
        - Press releases, correspondence about articles on trip (Box 410)
        - Tape dictated by Liz Abernathy (Box 410)
          (re. Japan, Korea, Manila, Vietnam, Singapore, Bangkok)
        - Clipping file (Box 410)
        - Nancy Williams letters home (Box 410)
          (originals)
        - GMW's letters to Nancy Williams (Box 410)
        - News releases of N. W.'s letters home (Box 410)
        - Newsclippings of N. W.'s letters home (Box 410)
        - Nancy Williams articles and correspondence about publication of letters (Box 410)
    - Staff Files
      The work of the Williams staff is documented throughout the major series of the collection. The records in Staff Files subseries relate mainly to the particular interests and activities of key staff members.
      - Charles Brown, 1958-1960
        The Charles Brown (Administrative Assistant) sub-subseries includes significant files concerning civil rights, unemployment, public works, and welfare relief.
        - Personal Papers
          - Congratulation letters, January 1958 (Box 410)
          - Newspaper clippings, circa 1958 (Box 410)
        - Topical Files
          - Administrative records, 1958-1959 (Box 410)
          - Aging, 1956-1960 (Box 410)
          - Agriculture
            - General, 1956-1960 (Box 410)
            - Migrant labor, 1958-1960 (Box 410)
          - Canadian off-shore oil, 1955-1959 (Box 410)
          - Civil Rights
            - General, 1958-1960 (Box 410)
            - Civil Rights Bill drafts, 1958-1959 (Box 410)
            - Second Governor's Conference on Civil Rights, January 31, 1959 (Box 410)
            - Willow Village Housing Problems, 1958-1959 (Box 410)
          - Conservation, 1958-1960 (Box 410)
          - Correspondence, February-December 1958 (Box 410)
          - Democratic Party in Michigan, 1958-1960 (Box 410)
          - Employment/Unemployment
            - General Unemployment, 1958-1960 (Box 410)
            - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, 1957-1958 (Box 411)
            - Fair Employment Practices Commission, 1959 (Box 411)
            - General Departmental Communication No. 17, December 21, 1959 (Box 411)
            - Michigan Employment Security Commission, 1958-1959 (Box 411)
            - Testimony before House Ways and Means committee, circa 1959 (Box 411)
          - Financial situation in Michigan, 1959 (Box 411)
          - Physically handicapped, 1959-1960 (Box 411)
          - Public Works
            - General, 1957-1960 (Box 411)
            - Replies from state departments, March 6, 1958 (Box 411)
            - Replies from local governments, March 14, 1958; 2 folders (Box 411)
            - Testimony before Banking and Currency Commission of House of Representatives, April 22, 1958 (Box 411)
          - Recreation Study Commission, 1959-1960 (Box 411)
          - Speeches
            - Governor's Message to Seventieth Michigan Legislature, January 1960 (Box 411)
            - Hampton Institute Commencement, June 2, 1958 (Box 411)
            - "Michigan's Great Future," (Box 411)
              (draft)
          - Steel strike, 1959 (Box 411)
          - Tourism, 1959-1960 (Box 411)
          - United States Forest Service, 1958-1960 (Box 411)
          - Visiting Nurse Association, 1957-1960 (Box 411)
          - Water Resources Commission, 1958-1960 (Box 411)
          - Waterways, 1958 (Box 411)
          - Welfare
            - Direct relief, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 411)
            - Surplus foods distribution (U. S. D. A. commodities), 1957-1959 (Box 411)
          - White House Conference of Children and Youth, 1960 (Box 411)
          - Miscellaneous/Fragmentary, 1958-1960 (Box 411)
      - Lawrence Farrell, 1949-1959
        Lawrence Farrell, served as Williams' executive secretary. The sub-subseries consists of a topical files, 1949-1959, mainly concerning departmental appointments and policy matters.
        - Activity Reports, 1957 (Box 412)
          (governor's hours and trips)
        - Auditor General, 1956 (Box 412)
        - Commission on Michigan's Economic Future, 1957-1958 (Box 412)
        - Cosmetology Board, 1954-1955 (Box 412)
        - Labor Department, 1956 (Box 412)
          (Re: John Reid)
        - Labor Mediation Board, 1958 (Box 412)
          (Re: Charles E. Coykenall)
        - Legislative Program, 1957-1958 (Box 412)
        - Liquor Control Commission
          - Complaints, 1956 (Box 412)
          - Requests for licenses, 1949-1951 (Box 412)
          - Regulations (Box 412)
          - Investigative Report of Liquor Control Commission, 1949-1951 (Box 412)
        - Mackinac Bridge Dedication, 1958 (Box 412)
        - Michigan Manufacturers Association, 1957 (Box 412)
        - National Gypsum (and Conservation Department), 1958 (Box 412)
        - Racing Department, 1957 (Box 412)
        - Social Welfare Boards (county), appointments, 1949-1959; 2 folders (Box 412)
          (scattered dates)
        - State Police, 1949-1950 (Box 412)
        - Tax Study Committee, 1957 (Box 412)
        - Taxes, 1957 (Box 412)
        - Upper Peninsula Natural Gas, 1957 (Box 412)
        - Woodfill, Stewart, 1957-1958 (Box 412)
        - Young Democrats, 1955-1956 (Box 412)
      - Jordan Popkin
        The files of Jordan Popkin (Administrative Assistant, and Chairman of Interdepartmental Commission on Problems of Aging) primarily concern issues relating to aging, particularly the work of the Commission on Aging.
        - Interdepartmental Committee on the Problems of Aging
          - 1950 (Box 412)
            (under James Magdanz)
            - Minutes (Box 412)
            - Correspondence and reports (Box 412)
            - Reports from other agencies (Box 412)
            - National Conference on Agin (Box 412)
              (addresses and reports)
          - 1956-1960
            - Correspondence from Governor on the revival of the Interdepartmental Committee on Problems of Aging, 1956 (Box 412)
            - Minutes and memoranda, 1956-1958 (Box 412)
            - Memoranda and reports, 1956-1958 (Box 412)
            - Recommendations to Governor, 1956-1958 (Box 412)
            - Materials from Governor's File on aging, 1956-1957 (Box 413)
            - Reports from other agencies, 1955-1958 (Box 413)
            - Reports of subcommittees, 1956; 1959 (Box 413)
            - Correspondence
              - 1955-1956 (Box 413)
              - 1957 (Box 413)
              - 1958 (Box 413)
              - 1959 (Box 413)
            - Materials for talks on Governor's program on aging (Box 413)
        - Commission on Aging
          - Minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 413)
          - Special File
            - 1959 (Box 413)
            - 1960 (Box 413)
          - Reports and correspondence, 1960 (Box 413)
          - Applications for executive secretary position, 1960 (Box 413)
        - Miscellaneous Aging Material
          - Aging, Conferences on, 1956; 1960 (Box 413)
            (correspondence and reports)
          - Citizens' Advisory Committee for White House Conference on Aging, 1959 (Box 413)
            (correspondence and memoranda)
          - Employment of the Older Worker, Governor's Commission on, 1959 (Box 413)
          - Federal Aging Survey Planning Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 413)
          - Health and welfare, legislative programs on (reports), 1954; 1956-1957 (Box 413)
          - Hill-Burton program, Governor's correspondence regarding, 1959-1960 (Box 413)
          - Legislative Advisory Council on Problems of the Aging, reports, 1956-1958 (Box 413)
          - Medical services for the aged and insurance, programs for, 1960 (Box 413)
            (correspondence and reports about)
          - Michigan Society of Gerontology, 1956-1959 (Box 413)
            (memoranda and correspondence)
          - Michigan Survey of Aging, materials on, 1958-1959 (Box 414)
          - Newspaper clippings, 1950-1960 (Box 414)
          - Senate Subcommittee on Problems of the Aged and Aging. Public Hearings, Grand Rapids, 1959 (Box 414)
            (reports)
      - John Sweeney
        The John Sweeney (Administrative Aide) sub-subseries is a topical file, covering the years 1956 and 1958.
        - Topical Files
          (mainly 1956 and 1958)
          - Aged (Box 414)
          - Agriculture (Box 414)
          - Atomic Power (Box 414)
          - Business and Industry (Box 414)
          - Campaign, 1956 (Box 414)
          - Conservation (Box 414)
          - Democratic party (Box 414)
          - Education (Box 414)
          - Foreign Aid (Point Four) (Box 414)
          - Foreign Policy (Box 414)
          - Health (Box 414)
          - Inter-office memoranda (Box 414)
          - Labor and Social Welfare (Box 414)
          - McCarran-Walter Act (Box 414)
          - Mackinac Bridge (Box 414)
          - McNamara, Patrick (and office) (Box 414)
          - Personal (Box 414)
          - Public Security (Box 414)
          - Recreation (Box 414)
          - States (Box 414)
            (correspondence from various states)
          - Veterans (Box 414)
          - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 414)
          - Miscellaneous subjects (Box 414)
      - Noel Fox, 1948-1960
        The files of Noel Fox, a long-time Williams aid, consists of a general correspondence file and papers concerning department of corrections. There is also a memorandum, written in 1959, concerning a 1947 party organization meeting.
        - Administration, Department of, 1949-1950 (Box 414)
        - Corrections, Department of
          - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 414)
          - Survey (Box 414)
          - Background material, 2 folders (Box 414)
        - Governor's Dinner, 1948 (Box 414)
        - Correspondence
          - 1948-1950 (Box 414)
          - 1951-1952 (Box 414)
          - 1953-1954 (Box 414)
          - 1955 (Box 414)
          - 1956-1960 (Box 414)
        - Memoranda, Re: party organization meeting in 1947, 1959 (Box 414)
      - William Monat, 1957-1960
        Administrative assistant William Monat's papers consist of a topical files, 1957-1960, concerning aging and other public policy subjects.
        - Topical files, 1957-1960
          - Atomic Energy (Box 415)
          - Banking (Box 415)
          - Capital Outlay (Box 415)
          - Citizens' Advisory Committee, White House Conference on Aging
            - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 415)
            - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 415)
          - Education (Box 415)
          - Federal-State Relations (Box 415)
          - Mental Health (Box 415)
          - Metropolitan Living, Study Commission on, 1958 (Box 415)
            (memoranda and reports)
          - Michigan's Economic Future, Committee on, 1957-1958 (Box 415)
          - Missiles and defense contracts, 1958-1959
            - Correspondence and reports (Box 415)
            - Newspaper clippings (Box 415)
          - Municipal Finance (Box 415)
          - Public Works - Full Employment (Box 415)
          - State Science Advisory Board, reports, 1958 (Box 415)
          - Tourism and Recreation (Box 415)
          - Water Resources (Box 415)
          - Welfare (Box 415)
      - Fred Tripp
        The Fred Tripp sub-subseries consists of a small topical file, 1954-1956.
        - Topical Files, 1954-1956
          - Aging (Box 415)
          - Agriculture (Box 415)
          - Education (Box 415)
          - Health and Welfare (Box 415)
          - Highways (Box 415)
          - Labor (Box 415)
          - Legislation/Working File (Box 415)
          - Parks and Recreation (Box 415)
          - Urban Planning Assistance (Box 415)
      - Edward Boucher
        Edward Boucher (Administrative Assistant) papers consist of topical files for 1960 only.
        - Topical Files, 1960
          - Agriculture (Box 415)
          - Alcoholism (Box 415)
          - Civil Service (Box 415)
          - Conservation (Box 416)
          - Michigan Employment Security Commission (Box 416)
          - Migrant Labor (Box 416)
          - Physically Handicapped (Box 416)
          - Recreation (Box 416)
          - Social Welfare (Box 416)
          - Soil Conservation (Box 416)
          - Tourism (Box 416)
          - Veterans Trust (Box 416)
          - Vocational Rehabilitation (Box 416)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 416)
      - John Abernethy
        The John Abernethy (Legislative Secretary) sub-subseries includes topical files, 1958-1960, and files on the governor's legislative program, 1957-1958.
        - Topical Files, 1958-1960
          - Appropriations
            - General (Box 416)
            - Waste (Box 416)
          - Bill Analyses (Box 416)
          - Budget (Box 416)
          - Cash Crisis (Box 416)
          - Children and Youth (Box 416)
          - Economy (Box 416)
          - Executive Staff (Box 416)
          - Housing Commission (Box 416)
          - Industrial Safety Advisory Council (Box 416)
          - Interim Committees (Box 416)
          - International Law (Box 416)
          - Legislative History, 1959 (Box 416)
          - Legislature (Box 416)
          - Recreation (Box 416)
          - Safety Commission (Box 416)
          - Taxes (Box 416)
        - Legislative Files, 1957-1958
          - Aging (Box 416)
          - Agriculture (Box 416)
          - Business and Industry (Box 417)
          - Civil Rights (Box 417)
          - Conservation (Box 417)
          - Education (Box 417)
          - General Government (Box 417)
          - Health (public and mental) (Box 417)
          - Housing (Box 417)
          - Labor (Box 417)
          - Safety (Box 418)
          - Social Welfare (Box 418)
          - Taxes (Box 418)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 418)
    - Miscellaneous
      The Miscellaneous subseries includes papers on various subjects unfiled at the time Williams left office. It consists, in part, of an arbitrarily created alphabetical sequence, including program projections for the years 1961-1965 that Williams asked the state's department heads to submit. The series also includes a chronological subseries of end-of-administration correspondence, November 1960 to January 1961. Much of this correspondence is of a perfunctory character.
      - Topical Files, 1955-1960
        - Administration, Department of (Box 418)
        - Africa, 2 folders (Box 418)
        - Astrology (Box 418)
        - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 418)
        - Automation (Box 418)
        - Captive European Nations (Box 418)
        - Civil Defense (Box 418)
        - Civil Rights (Box 418)
        - Commission, 2 folders, 1 volume (Box 418)
        - Financial, 1959 (Box 418)
        - Gift Lists (Box 419)
        - Health, Report on Michigan, 1938 (Box 419)
        - Inauguration
          - 1951 (Box 419)
          - 1953 (Box 419)
          - 1957 (Box 419)
        - Inflation (Box 419)
        - Isle Royale Trip, 1955 (Box 419)
        - Kozlov, Frol (GMW meeting with), 1959; 2 folders (Box 419)
        - McNaughton, Frank, 2 folders (Box 419)
        - Medical Care, Legislative Meeting on, 1960 (Box 419)
          (background material gathered in his biography of GMW)
        - Mentally Retarded (Box 419)
        - NAACP tribute to GMW (Box 419)
        - Power Reactor Development (Box 420)
        - Program Projections for, 1961-1965
          - General (Box 420)
          - Adult Corrections (Box 420)
          - Conservation, recreation and agriculture (Box 420)
          - Education (Box 420)
          - General Government (Box 420)
          - Public Welfare (Box 420)
          - Regulatory (Box 420)
          - Restricted Funds (Box 420)
          - Safety and Defense (Box 420)
        - Reapportionment (Box 420)
        - Segregation (Box 420)
        - Stevens, Floyd (Box 420)
          (scrapbook about job applicant)
        - Washington trips, 1955; 1957 (Box 420)
        - Williams, Gerhard (Box 420)
          (hearing before U. S. Senate)
        - Williams, Nancy (Box 420)
        - Williams Family (Box 420)
      - Late Filings
        - November 1960-January 1961 (Box 420)
        - November 1960-January 1961 (Box 421)
      - Assorted Papers
        - Unprocessed and loose materials (Box 421)
        - Correspondence, reports to Governor, press releases, etc. (Box 422)
  - Press Office, 1949-1960
    The Press Office series contains materials generated or collected by the governor's press office. It is divided into ten subseries: Speeches, Messages to the Legislature, Radio Talks, Weekly Press Column, Press Releases, Schedules, Appointment Books, Topical File and Miscellaneous.
    - Speeches, 1949-1960
      - 1949-1951 (Box 423)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 424)
      - 1954-February 1955 (Box 425)
      - March 1955-April 1956 (Box 426)
      - May 1956-1957 (Box 427)
      - January-October 1958 (Box 428)
      - November 1958-February 1960 (Box 429)
      - March-December 1960 (Box 430)
    - Messages to the Legislature, 1949-1960
      - 1949-1955 (Box 430)
      - 1956-1960 (Box 431)
    - Radio and Television
      - Radio Talks, 1949-1954 (Box 431)
        - 1949-June 1950 (Box 431)
        - October 1950-1954 (Box 432)
      - Radio/TV Files (Paul Weber)
        - Stations [A-C] (Box 432)
        - Stations [D-T] (Box 433)
        - Subject Files (Box 433)
      - Speech Miscellanea (Box 434)
    - Weekly Newspaper Column
      - 1950-1960 (Box 434)
    - Press Releases, December 1948-1960
      - December 1948-June 1954 (Box 435)
      - July 1954-February 1958 (Box 436)
      - March 1958 - February 1960 (Box 437)
      - March-December 1960 (Box 438)
    - Schedules, 1949-1960
      - 1949-1950 (Box 438)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 439)
      - 1956-1960 (Box 440)
    - Appointment Books, 1949-1960
      - 1949-1954 (Box 441)
      - 1955-1960 (Box 442)
    - Topical Files
      Press Office Topical files, 1950-1960, include clippings, published material, press releases, copies of correspondence and memoranda on political and public policy issues; also files on state and national personalities.
      - Absenteeism to Aged (Box 443)
      - Agriculture to American Banker (Box 444)
      - American Bar Association to Automobile Negotiations, 1958 (Box 445)
      - Bagwell to Bridge Commission (Box 446)
      - Broomfield to Budget (Box 447)
      - Budget (cont.) to Campaign, 1950 (Box 448)
      - Campaign 1950 to Campaign, 1960, 1950-1960 (Box 449)
      - Canvassers to Chamber of Commerce (Box 450)
      - Chamberlain to Civil Rights, 1956 (Box 451)
      - Civil Rights 1957 to Communism, 1952, 1952-1957 (Box 452)
      - Communism to Conservation, 1953 (Box 453)
      - Conservation to Corrections, 1952 (Box 454)
      - Corrections 1953 to Democratic Party, 1952, 1952-1953 (Box 455)
      - Democratic Party to Democratic Party, 1960, 1953 (Box 456)
      - Dentistry to Economic Development, 1954 (Box 457)
      - Economic Development 1955 to Education, 1956, 1955-1956 (Box 458)
      - Education to Efficiency Board of Review, 1957 (Box 459)
      - Election to Employment Security, 1956 (Box 460)
      - Employment Security (cont.) to Extradition (Box 461)
      - Fact Book to Fleming, Clyde (Box 462)
      - Floods to Governors' Conference (Box 463)
      - Grand Jury to Health (Box 464)
      - Hemans to Inland Governors' Conference (Box 465)
      - Inside Michigan to Khrushchev (Box 466)
      - Kiwanis to Legislature, 1952 (Box 467)
      - Legislature to Liquor Control Commission, 1953 (Box 468)
      - Lithuania to Mental Health, 1951 (Box 469)
      - Mental Health (cont.) to Message to Legislature, 1951 (Box 470)
      - Metropolitan Areas to Mortuary Science (Box 471)
      - Moses, James M. to Mortuary Science (Box 472)
      - Pittsburgh Courier to Public Service Commission, 1950 (Box 473)
      - Public Service Commission to Reconstruction Finance Corporation, 1951 (Box 474)
      - Recount to Road Program, 1950 (Box 475)
      - Roads 1951 to Roads, 1958, 1951-1958 (Box 476)
      - Roads to St. Lawrence Seaway, 1959 (Box 477)
      - Salaries to Stahlin, John H. (Box 478)
      - State, Department of to Straits Bridge, 1957 (Box 479)
      - Straits Bridge 1958 to Taxes, 1952, 1952-1958 (Box 480)
      - Taxes 1953 to Taxes, 1959, 1953-1959 (Box 481)
      - Taxes (cont.) to Tax subject files, 1959 (Box 482)
      - Tax subject files (cont.) to Tornadoes (Box 483)
      - Tourists to United Press (Box 484)
      - United Rubber Workers to Weeklies, 1950 (Box 485)
      - Weeklies, 1951 to Williams (Box 486)
      - Williams (cont.) to Zielenski (Box 487)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Press Releases/Correspondence, 1960
        - General (Box 488)
        - Appointment as Secretary of State for African Affairs (Box 488)
        - Controller Ira Polley (Box 488)
      - Controller James W. Miller, 1958-1959 (Box 488)
      - Miscellaneous, 1959-1960 (Box 488)
      - Clippings/Briefings (Box 488)